hi Dr Grant trt cream is becoming
increasingly more accepted I would like
to hear everything you know about the
cream so that's probably a lot what what
percentage of men do well on compounded
cream maybe let's start with that um I
mean I don't know in general all I can
tell you is my own experience as far as
who do who does well um I will say the
majority of men that I get on cream stay
on cream uh I have a lot of guys that
switch from injections to cream and I
would say the majority so greater than
50% stick with the cream some go back to
injections just because not either it
didn't didn't absorb well for them
honestly that's rare I would say it's
more of a uh convenience factor some
guys just prefer not having to apply
something every day or twice a day and
that's fine um but as far as the uh
efficacy if you if you Source it
properly know your compounding pharmacy
trust their product know that you've had
good experience with it you know
consistently over time uh make sure it's
the right base and sometimes you got to
play with that stuff but it works really
well for most people and I and I can
just tell you anecdotally speaking and
personally that um it was a game changer
for me um you know as far as how I felt
and the mental the mental Clarity side
of things was what really changed and
you know Eric Serrano mentioned that we
were at Silverback Summit back in
November with Ally and and even he had
mentioned on stage up there that his
patients on cream just they just feel
better mentally they just have less
brain fog and I I can 100% a test to
that is that true across the board no
but I don't think this this fear people
have that oh it's topical it must not be
as good they think that just because
you're injecting something in the body
that it makes it better um that may be
true as far as just getting a blood
level um but all things being equal if
you absorb cream well you it's really
just personal preference and Andor
efficacy you know some guys just feel
better with the cream so I can't tell
you everything about cream as far as
like how are they sourcing it and what
are they doing as far as truly making it
I I haven't I haven't watched the
compounding pharmacy put it together um
I just know that they've come up with
ways to do it that seem to
absorb pretty remarkably well actually
I've been pretty impressed with it um
and it's the same for females right like
they've got all these different bases
now um certain bases that that go better
like on the vaginal mucosa that wouldn't
go well on just the normal skin and then
other bases that seem to go anywhere you
can do fine and so it really is trial
and error I usually use a trious base
but also HRT base or HRT heavy base I
like a lot uh some guys prefer Versa I
kind of go with Atrius first off and
then if that doesn't seem to work well
or if they get a skin rash or something
like that we'll switch to HRT base um my
wife for females uses What's called the
elage base it's more of a um it's a
thinner it's not really even as cream
it's almost like a lotion um but yeah
cream in general um it's just it's
becoming more accepted because it works
well I saw a trt clinic or some an owner
of a TR Clin T Clinic the other day on
Instagram posting something about
injections and these are the best way to
do trt and it's like that that's like
saying vanilla is the best flavor of ice
cream it just doesn't it's it's
subjective um and or it's we'll say it's
objective in a way but also subjective
for the individual um everybody's
different so I think I tell my guys you
kind of if you're on the fence about it
try it if you if you can get it if you
if you trust your provider they know
where to Source it I I think you owe it
to yourself if you're not feeling great
um you kind of owe it to yourself to at
least try it like Mark it off the list
if it doesn't work for you but that's
what I tell my guys new patients that
come to me if they've never taken
testosterone I try to kind of steer them
to cream first because it's a lot of
them don't want M with learning
injections and I'm like if the cream
works well for you you'll probably stay
with it if it doesn't again that's good
because we know hey it just didn't work
well for you let's mark it off the list
and let's play with the injection side
of things so but um anyway I hope that's
kind of a vague answer as far as tell me
everything you know about cream but in
general I will say And as far as a few
and I know there's controversial people
disagree with this but I do not see the
elevations in hemoglobin hematocrite on
cream like we do on injections it just
doesn't doesn't tend to happen um do I
think anything of that not really I
think it's interesting I don't I don't
tell guys to donate you know even if
they're on injections if they're running
High per se that's so it's not like I
think hematocrit is a problem but I do
find it fascinating that we're not
seeing you know those issues with guys
on um sorry I think it broke up for a
minute I think it's fascinating we're
not seeing the the hematic issues on the
cream and it makes me think there's
something in the
injectable other than the testosterone
that's causing that whether it's the
injection of the oil or preservative
something that stimulates that red blood
cell production more than a cream wood
so it's
interesting another question he said uh
are certain compounding pharmacies more
reliable than others or are they all
fairly competent well it's all over the
board man like you it's so frustrating
you would think oh I'll just go to my
local compounder and and get it made and
it'll be and that's not how it works you
got they've gota just like anywhere else
they have to take seriously what they do
and enjy what they do uh do it right do
it well and not all of them do and I had
issues with guys who've used small
Compounders before and like their first
set of labs are great and then a couple
months go by and they start you know
they're like Doc I don't feel good this
month I feel like there's I'm not on my
testosterone anymore I'm like well let's
check some blood work and um we check it
and their levels are 3 400 um and I'm
like you know did you put your cream on
you do everything the same yep sure did
and I've had that happen enough so I'll
switch them to like medquest which is a
mega compounding pharmacy out of Utah
and then we never have that issue again
so it is kind of interesting and so I
tend to go with Med Quest unless
somebody has a preference and they just
want to try local um because I just
never know you know and I'm like if
you're gonna try do it with the best
possible route that you can with the
most reputable pharmacy at least at
first once they kind of dial in on their
cream if they want to try a smaller
compounder to compare go for it but a
lot of them are pretty happy with the
the bigger brand and it's the same price
honestly they're very affordable either
way so um but yeah there's they're all
over the map I can't remember I think it
was four or five years ago maybe may
have been Keith Nichols that talked
about a study done I think on
Compounders in Canada and they were
testing different amounts of
testosterone I think it was testosterone
in cream and it was all over the map as
far some were like 0% I mean it's just
how does that
this just means they didn't actually get
it in solution or whatever like it just
completely crashed um and that's the
other thing you don't want I've noticed
some compounding phes will say they can
do up to a 30% strength cream I would
probably stick with 20 or less I think
you're playing with fire getting up into
that 30 range or more where it may just
may just crash and you don't get
anything out of it
so um how long should one wait before
adjusting the protocol with cream
because um the results are more rap it
down with injections they are they're
quicker I usually tell guys honestly at
first when it's when you're first
starting testosterone I still like them
to give I I check blood work at a month
to make just to make sure they're not
wasting their money on it um if their
numbers are quote unquote good at that
four-week Mark I usually tell them hey
either write it out where you're at or
if you want to add a click do that and
then after they and once they do that
once they start adjusting I think
usually with a couple two to three weeks
they can kind of tell on the cream
what's happening um in in fact some guys
know within a day or two honestly it's
that potent um because there's no Esther
attached right they're not waiting for
this whole time release and I know
theoretically once your blood levels are
a certain amount with injections you
should still notice those differences
but it just doesn't seem to work like
that I mean everybody's different some
guys swear they can feel even injections
on one day you know but in general I do
tend to say don't spend as much time
waiting it out on the cream as I would
somebody on injections you know three to
four weeks on cream versus six to eight
weeks on an injection protocol let's
just say yeah the typical worry people
also have is uh is it possible for DHD
to get too high with creams again we're
back into that hole what is how do you
test that right because DHT serum levels
are going to be the same issue as you
have with estradiol levels
where are you getting an accurate
reflection of overall DHT production um
or at the tissue level you don't know
you don't know in what tissue is it high
and what tissue is it low getting just a
snapshot of serum levels doesn't
actually tell you what's going on at the
tissue level so that's where I get a
little it's like I hear all this stuff
about oh yeah cream converts more to DHT
I I haven't ever looked into that
because I don't care about the serum in
DHT levels so I'm not really gonna go
off that I don't know if anybody's ever
done a study on that looking at that I
think it doesn't matter here here's the
thing whatever the story is you know
people always do this they confuse their
effects with the story underneath so if
you feel worse when you go up in your
dose on cream it doesn't matter if that
feeling worse was from DHT or increase
free testosterone or whatever drop your
dose back down to see if you can feel
better you know uh this idea that we
need to start quote quote balancing
these other hormones the body is the
best at balancing it knows what it's
doing that's that's how it's made
especially when it's when we're talking
about conversion processes that we can't
even really measure that we just think
are going on and so it's like just be
careful with getting into those rabbit
Trails of thought with worried about DHT
or worried about estr or this it's like
big picture dose response adjust based
on symptoms like stay out of the weeds
with constantly worried about the lab
stuff that's my own
personal opinion on that